Preliminary Guide to the Western Farmers Association Records 1923-1981
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Preliminary Guide to the Western Farmers Association Records
1923-1981
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
MSSM 062
Western Farmers Association
14 Linear feet of shelf space 15 Boxes
Western Farmers Association records, including correspondence, publications, ledgers (minutes), photographs, reports.
The Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association (also referred to as the Washington Co-Operative Farmers Association) was formed in 1917. The original organization was a collection of cooperatives, including the Whatcom County Egg Producers, the Whidbey Island Cooperative Egg Farms, and the Silverdale Poultry Association, with collaboration from Washington State College's Western Washington Experiment Station. The cooperative became affiliated with the Pacific Egg Producers in 1922, and began publishing the weekly journal "WASHCOEGG" in 1923. The journal transitioned into the "Western Farmer" in 1960, and publishing continued until 1981. During this period, the name of the organization was changed to the Western Farmers Association. The Western Farmers Association was acquired by CENEX in 1981.
This collection contains records of the Western Farmers Association (formerly the Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association), including correspondence, publications, ledgers (minutes), photographs, and reports. It includes a complete run of the association's journals "WASHCOEGG" and "Western Farmer". The collection also contains copies of a publication on the history of the Washington Co-Operative Farmers Association from 1917 to 1956, audit reports, and various papers pertaining to the organization and other local cooperatives.
This is an unprocessed collection. Any arrangement reflects either a pre-existing order from the records' creators or previous custodians, or preliminary sorting performed by staff.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Bob Eschbach donated these materials to the Washington State University Libraries in 1983 (MS.1983.03) and 1984 (MS.1984.21).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Western Farmers Association -- Records and correspondence.
Agriculture -- Washington (State); Poultry -- Breeding -- History -- Sources.
Agriculture
- Preliminary Inventory
  - MS.1983.03
    - Bell, R.C., and W.D. Buchanan. "Partners in Progress: The Story of Washington Co-Operative Farmers Association." Circa 1956; Papers related to the Washington Co-operative Egg and Poultry Association (or Washington Co-Operative Farmers Association) and the Western Farmers Association, including brochures and guides, bylaws, correspondence, business contracts, newspaper clippings, industry reports, as well as materials pertaining to 4-H and FFA, and papers related to the manuscript for "Partners in Progress", circa 1920s-1970s. (Box 1)
    - Photographs and negatives related to Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association, and meeting minutes from various egg and poultry cooperatives, circa 1920s-1930s, a guestbook, papers and photographs related to Central Farmer Industries, as well as reports related to a Petroleum Refinery Study. (Box 2)
    - Bound items pertaining to project specification from the Cooperative Refinery (Vancouver, WA). (Box 3)
    - Memorandum, copy of "Partners in Progress," and negatives related to Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association. (Box 4)
    - Bound audit reports for the Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association, 1932-1954; reports related to a Petroleum Refinery Study. (Box 5)
    - Photographs, slides, and negatives related to Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Association. (Box 6)
  - MS.1984.21
    - Washington Co-Operative Egg and Poultry Association's Audit Report (1928); WASHCOEGG, 1923 - 1931. (Box 1)
    - WASHCOEGG, 1931-1939. (Box 2)
    - WASHCOEGG, 1939-1952. (Box 3)
    - WASHCOEGG, 1952-1960, and Western Farmer, 1960-1965. (Box 4)
    - Western Farmer, 1965-1981. (Box 5)
    - Materials related to the National Council of Farmer Cooperatives, including photographs and negatives, 1955-1980; Food Industries, Volumes 10-17, 1938-1945. (Box 6)
    - Photographs, negatives, slides related to the Washington Co-Operative Farmers Association, 1955-1980. (Box 7)
    - Photographs, negatives, slides, and two scrapbooks, 1924-1981, including older photographs related to the Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Associations in Tacoma and Seattle. (Box 8)
    - Photographs and negatives related to the Washington Cooperative Egg and Poultry Associations. (Box 9)